A Guide to the Papers of W.B. Shafer, Jr. 1939-1981
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
The Papers of W.B. Shafer, Jr. 1939-1981
Special Collections, Perry Library, Old Dominion University
MG 52
9 Hollinger Document Cases, and 1 Oversize Box
Administrative Information
Access
Open to researchers without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift from W.B. Shafer, February 1982.
Biographical/Historical Information
W. Bruce Shafer was an idealist and a philanthropist. He was an industrious promoter and "booster" of ideas, projects, Norfolk, and even himself. To some he was an eccentric, while others considered him a genius. Shafer was a Methodist and a Mason. He was religious and conservative. He did not necessarily ally himself with either political party. Shafer was more about morals and issues than party.
Shafer was born in 1894 in Norfolk County. His father was a produce broker, and the family business went broke the year Shafer graduated from Norfolk Academy (1912). W.B. Shafer, Jr. went to work shipping produce. A few years later, he and his father jointly founded a firm that became one of Norfolk's most successful produce brokers. In his youth, Shafer served on several bank boards, financed farmers, and wrote books about finance and honesty. Although Shafer himself did not fight in World War I, he still did his part. He originated and financed "The Potato Publicity and Wheat League" which helped farmers and prevented a food shortage. After the war, Shafer originated the World War I Soldier Bonus and contributed $50,000 to the campaign between 1918 and 1936.
Shafer ran for Norfolk City Council in 1928, and claims the election was stolen from him. The experience disenchanted him from local politics. He ran for Congress in 1944 as an independent. He tried again for Norfolk City Council in 1966. Despite his disenfranchisement with politics, he was advisor to two presidents, Franklin D. Roosevelt and Calvin Coolidge, as well as friend and supporter of many Congressmen.
Shafer was a big "booster" of the Norfolk and Southern economic booms. He spent over $100,000 in ads boosting the South. He also wrote books, booklets, flyers, and newsletters promoting Norfolk, Dallas, and the South to realtors, investors, governors, congressmen, and others. He advocated for the local bridge-tunnels, better highways, and the Dismal Swamp Canal to make Hampton Roads more accessible to businesses. His hard work and foresight brought businesses into Ward's Corner and Military Circle. He was also involved with the development of Fox Hall and Norview.
Shafer's other projects included a world peace plan to put a chaplain in each embassy to cultivate friendship, a prosperity plan to bring advertising money to the South, and a "religious reformation" movement. He directed his energy to oppose corruption in government and the Norfolk City Council, the Norfolk news monopoly, "hippy communism," and other things he thought were wrecking America.
Shafer was a prolific writer about his ideas. Besides newsletters, flyers, and correspondence, he wrote several books and booklets including: "How to Make a Fortune Honestly and Quickly," "Go South Young Man, Go South Where God Still Lives," "Success and Happiness," "3 Books that Made the South and 1000 Millionaires and 10 Billionaires," and "Washington and the New Economic South."
Despite frequent complaints about his health and age, Shafer lived to the ripe old age of 95. He passed away in 1990. True to his life, his tombstone promotes the ideals and causes he lived for.
Scope and Content Information
This collection contains information about the Norfolk and Southern economic booms of the 1950s and 1960s, Shafer's real estate and investing ventures during that same time period, the political issues and causes that he advanced, his charitable donations, books and newsletters that he wrote, and various correspondence. Except for correspondence, much of the material in this collection is undated. The majority of this collection spans the mid-1950s through the end of the 1970s. A small amount of material is dated in the 1930s, 1940s, and 1980s.
Organization
This collection is broken down into the following series: I. Projects, Issues, and Causes; II. Philanthropy and Religious Charities; III. Correspondence; IV. Books, Essays, and Other Publications; V. Miscellaneous; and VI. Artifacts.
Series I. Projects, Issues, and Causes. This series is divided into four subseries. Subseries A: Norfolk Boom and Boosting; Subseries B: Real Estate and Investing; Subseries C: Political Issues; and Subseries D: Politics.
Subseries A: Norfolk Boom and Boosting. This subseries contains information about the Norfolk and Southern Economic Booms of the 1950s and 1960s. Information included are Norfolk Boom and Investment maps, flyers, and postcards; correspondence, news, and articles on the Norfolk, Dallas, and Southern Booms; information on the Norfolk, Virginia and Carolina Booster Club; and material on Military Circle, the Chesapeake Bay Bridge-Tunnel, the Virginia Highway System, and the Dismal Swamp Canal as related to bringing business into the Hampton Roads area.
Subseries B: Real Estate and Investing. This subseries contains information about the real estate and investing ventures of Shafer. Included are property deeds, contracts, and survey maps; correspondence and promotional material related to real estate; information on the Greater Norfolk Investors and other investment companies; investing information on railroads, steel plants, and shopping centers; and real estate and industrial directories.
Subseries C: Political Issues. This subseries contains information on local and national political issues and projects advanced by Shafer. Topics include potato and produce overheads and exports, the Shafer Peace Plan, the Shafer Prosperity Plan, the Peace Temple at Cape Henry, Religious Reformation of America, Employment for War Veterans, gasoline prices, abortion, race relations, the poll tax, unions, the American monetary system, Vietnam, communism, bond issues, the Norfolk news monopoly, Norfolk Gardens, and an art museum at Military Highway. This subseries also includes newspaper clippings and letters to newspaper editors on these and other issues.
Subseries D: Politics. This subseries contains information on local and national politics, as well as correspondence between Shafer and various political figures including City Councilmen, Congressmen, Senators, Governors, and Presidents. Content of these letters includes the Norfolk and Southern booms, real estate and investing, communism, letters of support, and other subjects of concern to Shafer. Additional topics include corruption in the Norfolk City Council, Shafer's bid for Norfolk City Council, Mafia involvement in the government, Watergate, the 1976 Presidential election, the Republican party, and congressional reform. Of particular note in this subseries is a signed Christmas card from President Jimmy Carter, as well as letters written to several presidents and FBI director J. Edgar Hoover.
Series II. Philanthropy and Religious Charities. This series includes information about various charities and religious organizations that Shafer supported. Included are entries and information on the W.B. Shafer Award Competition Contest for high school students; Jerry Falwell's Old Time Gospel Hour, Liberty Baptist College, and Mercy Ship; other schools, churches, and religious organizations; and Cal Farley's Boys Ranch.
Series III. Correspondence. Although there is a great deal of correspondence scattered throughout this collection, this series contains both personal correspondence and correspondence that does not readily fit into the other series. This series includes correspondence between Shafer and banks, corporations, and attorneys on various issues; invitations, cards, and letters regarding Shafer's health. This series also consists of blank greeting cards, blank Western Union and Postal forms, blank holiday cards from charitable organizations, and Shafer's stationary and mailing labels.
Series IV. Books, Essays, and Other Publications. This series is divided into four subseries. Subseries A: Essays/Newsletters; Subseries B: Shafer's Books; Subseries C: Newspapers and Magazines; and Subseries D: Advertising.
Subseries A: Essays/Newsletters. This subseries includes essays and newsletters written by Shafer. Topics include real estate and investing; political corruption; drugs and hippy communism; the Norfolk News monopoly; the Peace Prayer Temple at Cape Henry; Shafer's contributions; Religious Reformation; and other issues of concern to Shafer.
Subseries B: Shafer's Books. This subseries includes book publicity; requests for his books and thank you letters for their receipt; requests for essays to be included in future books; information on book publishers; rough drafts for the book "How to Make a Fortune Quickly and Honestly"; and final copies of Shafer's books "How to Make a Fortune Quickly and Honestly," "Investment Success and Happiness," "3 Books that Made the South and 1000 Millionaires and 10 Billionaires," "Go South Young Man, Go South Where God Still Lives."
Subseries C: Newspapers and Magazines. This subseries contains copies of newspapers and magazines related to politics, religion, veterans, and real estate and investing.
Subseries D: Advertising. This subseries contains receipts for the printing of some of Shafer's promotional material; advertising rates and information for "The Spotlight"; other newspapers and magazines; television and radio station advertising policies; and receipts for air time. This subseries also includes a few copies of classified ads that were placed by Shafer on the Norfolk Boom, gasoline prices, and religious reformation.
Series V. Miscellaneous. This series contains material that does not necessarily fit into any of the other series of this collection. The most notable items in this series are the photographs, including photos of Shafer's tombstone, and a rough draft of his last will and testament. This series also includes information on Shafer's trip to Hot Springs; various receipts, warranties, and instruction manuals; information on psychics; miscellaneous notes, lists, articles, and booklets; and other miscellaneous material.
Series VI. Artifacts. This series contains artifacts that are a part of this collection. Included are a ministry audiocassette by Jerry Falwell; a refill for a Pallotine Pen by Pallotine Missionaries; a box of Buss Auto Fuses; and "Easy Do" remote switch; and a "Wm. Crooks-Minnesota Pioneer" limited run lithograph.
Contents List
- Projects, Issues, and Causes
  - Norfolk Boom and Boosting
    - Norfolk Boom Maps (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Norfolk Investments Maps (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Boom Flyers and Postcards (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 3)
    - More Boom Promotion (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Letters Requesting Boom Maps, 1959-1965 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Dallas Boom (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Boosting the South-Other Cities (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 7)
    - More Literature on the Economic Boom in the South (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Letters, Articles on Economic Success of the South (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 9)
    - More Articles and Letters about the South (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Newspaper Clippings: Norfolk Boom (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Norfolk Booster Club (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Booster Club-Resolutions (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Virginia and Carolina Booster Club Directors (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Military Circle (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Chesapeake Bay Bridge-Tunnel: Promotional Material (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Chesapeake Bay Bridge-Tunnel: Tunnel Articles and Letters I (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Chesapeake Bay Bridge-Tunnel: Tunnel Articles and Letters II (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Chesapeake Bay Bridge-Tunnel: Boom Flyers/Maps (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Chesapeake Bay Bridge-Tunnel: Newspaper Clippings (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Virginia Highways (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Dismal Swamp (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Dismal Swamp Industrial Canal Committee, Inc. I (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Dismal Swamp Industrial Canal Committee, Inc. II (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Real Estate and Investing
    - Real Estate (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Real Estate-Promotional Material (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Real Estate-Correspondence, 1956-1970 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Letters from Huckins Hotel, Oklahoma City, Oklahoma, 1969 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Real Estate Deeds and Contracts, 1959-1960, 1965, 1976 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Webb-Shafer Contract, 1962 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 6)
    - W.B. Shafer Purchase of Matilda Bell, 1947-1948 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Purchase of Council, 1947 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Sale of Property to Andrew Holding Corporation, 1956 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Real Estate-Survey Maps (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Greater Norfolk Investors (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Virginia and Carolina Investors Corporation (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Investment Corporations, Realty, Sales Companies (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Tidewater Association of Home Builders (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Railroad Companies (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Steel Plant (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Big Town and Other Shopping Centers (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Virginia Real Estate Directory-Bulletin, April 1939 Licensed (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Industrial Directory-TVDC, 1960-1961 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Political Issues
    - Potatoes and Produce (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Shafer Peace Plan (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Shafer Prosperity Plan (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Peace Temple at Cape Henry (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Religious Reformation (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Engrossed House Concurrent Resolution No. 1004 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Vietnam (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 7)
    - 50 Million Dollar Bond Issue (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Employment for War Veterans (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Loyalty Celebration for Veterans in Congress (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Veterans Appeal Board (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 11)
    - V.F.W. (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Preliminary Non-Partisan Veterans Committee (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Increase in Gasoline Price (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Abortion (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Race Relations (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Sex, Drugs, Communism in Schools (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Hippy Communism (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 18)
    - AFL-CIO/Unions (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Cooperators for Constitutional Money (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Norfolk News Monopoly (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Tennessee Firm to Stop P.M. Paper, February 25, 1970 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Norfolk Gardens (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Art Museum at Military Circle (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Letters to Editors, 1976-1978 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Poll Tax, Water Plant, News Clippings (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Newspaper Clippings (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Politics
    - Shafer for Norfolk City Council, 1966 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Shafer on Democratic Ticket, 1944 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Norfolk City Council (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Norfolk City Council-Corruption (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Norfolk Counties and Cities-All Cities in Virginia, 1956-1962, 1970-1971 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Cities, Administration Department Letters: Out of State Cities, States, 1956-1965 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Letters from Virginia Governor's Office, 1956-1976 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Virginia Legislative Directory, 1977-1981 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Letters From State of North Carolina, 1956-1964, 1976 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Letters from Executive Department and Head Officers, 1939-1977 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Watergate (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Newspaper Clippings: Watergate Scandal (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Watergate, Mafia Involvement in the Government (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 4)
    - 1976 Election (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Resolution: 1976 Convention Republican Party Heading for Deadlock (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Billion Dollar Bi-Partisan Mafia, 1977 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 7)
    - The Reform that Wasn't, February 14, 1977 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Support for Candidates, 1944, 1956, 1974, 1977 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 9)
    - President Lyndon B. Johnson (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 10)
    - President Richard Nixon (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 11)
    - President Gerald Ford (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 12)
    - President Jimmy Carter (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 13)
    - India Warmth for Carter Kin, February 14, 1977 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Ronald Reagan, 1980 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Press Conference with Ronald Reagan, November 20, 1975 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Letters from Congress of the United States Part I: 1950s (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Letters from Congress of the United States Part II: 1960s (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Letters from Congress of the United States Part III: 1970s (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Letters from United States Senate Part I: 1950s (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Letters from United States Senate Part II: 1960s-1970s (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Victor Wickersham, 1965-1969 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Lloyd Bentsen, 1975-1976 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Senator A.J. Gronna Funeral, 1966 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Senate, House, Governor Listings (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Miscellaneous Political (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 26)
- Philanthropy and Religious Charities
  - The W.B. Shafer Award Competition Contest, 1969-1970 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Jerry Falwell urging others to donate to keep the Old Time Gospel Hour on the Air, 1978-1981 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Religious Reformations by Jerry Falwell: Cleaning Up America, 1978-1980 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Liberty Baptist College Needs Monetary Aid to Keep Functioning, 1978-1981 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Jerry Falwell Requesting Money To Keep Mercy Ship Alive: Missionary Society, 1978-1981 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Religious Organizations and Churches (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Virginia Wesleyan College, 1971-1978 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Liberty Baptist College and Other Universities (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Norfolk Academy (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Cal Farley's Boys Ranch (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 10)
- Correspondence
  - Banks and Corporation, 1956-1964 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Letters from Kellam and Kellam Attorneys and Counselors at Law, 1956-1966 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Kellam, Pickrell, and Lawler Attorneys and Counselors at Law, 1970-1981 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Attorneys at Law, Other Letters from Law Counselors, 1957-1979 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Luncheon Invitations, March 2, 1970 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Personal Letters and Papers to Shafer, 1956-1979 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Letters of Sympathy to Shafer Regarding His Health (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Holiday Cards, Sympathy, and Thank You Cards (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Blank Stationary (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Shafer Mailing Labels (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Greeting Cards I (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Greeting Cards II (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Blank Western Union Telegram and Postal Forms (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 13)
- Books, Essays, and Other Publications
  - Essays/Newsletters
    - Essays by Shafer (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Article: They Think You Are Too Dumb To Run Virginia (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 2)
    - The Hazards of Standing Up for Pariahs, February 20, 1970 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Norfolk News Monopoly Slants the News Against Mr. Shafer, November 13, 1969 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Million Dollar Peace-Prayer Temple for Cape Henry Will Double Our Exports (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Biggest Booster Recognized, November 13, 1969 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Shafer Newsletters (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 7)
    - (WIWA) What is Wrecking America Drafted from God (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 8)
    - History About Virginia and Carolina (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Shafer's Books
    - Shafer Book Publicity (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Requests for Book Submissions (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Requests for Shafer's Books (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Book Publishers (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Pages from Shafer's Books (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Draft of Book: How to Make a Fortune Quickly and Honestly Part I (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Draft of Book: How to Make a Fortune Quickly and Honestly Part II (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Book: How to Make a Fortune Quickly and Honestly (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Shafer Books: Investment Success and Happiness, How to Make a Fortune (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 18)
    - 3 Books That Made the South and 1000 Millionaires and 10 Billionaires (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 19)
    - 2nd Copy of 3 Books That Made the South and 1000 Millionaires and 10 Billionaires (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Book: Go South Young Man, Go South Where God Still Lives (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Book: Washington and the New Economic South (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Newspapers and Magazines
    - Newspaper Articles from the Spotlight: Part I (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Newspaper Articles from the Spotlight: Part II (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Newspaper Articles from the Spotlight: Part III (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Navy Newspaper (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Navy News (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 8)
    - World Ports and Marine News, December, 1964 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Human Potential Published by the Ambassador International Cultural Foundation, March/April, 1976 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Virginia Veteran Official Publication of the Veterans of Foreign Wars of the United States, Volume XXIV (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Bible Advocate May 79, National Real Estate (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Virginia Veteran (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Magazines: World Ports Marine News, January 1964; The National Real Estate Investor, March 1960; Houston Regional Business News Magazine, November 1964; Bank of the Southwest Annual Report, 1963 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Advertising
    - Printing (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 5)
    - The Spotlight Newspaper (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Classified Ads from the Spotlight, Newspaper Classified Ads on Gasoline and Oil Prices (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Newspaper Ads (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Newspaper and Magazines (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Radio and TV (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 10)
- Miscellaneous
  - Hot Springs (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Last Will and Testament (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Shafer Photographs (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Income Tax (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous Receipts and Warranties (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 15)